So now that we implemented auto logout when our token expires and no worries, we'll turn our heads towards
Bu nedenle, belirtecimizin sresi dolduunda ve endie duyulmadnda otomatik oturum kapatma ilemini uyguladk, daha sonra
adjusting the layout depending on the authentication state later too,
kimlik dorulama durumuna bal olarak dzeni ayarlamak iin
now that we get the auto logout implemented,
kafalarmz dndreceiz. Artk, otomatik
let's turn our heads towards using that token to make requests to protected resources.
oturum kapatma ilemini gerekletirdik, bamz bu jetonu kullanmaya ynlendirelim Korunan kaynaklara talepte bulunmak.
That's of course a typical use case, you have a backend with certain API endpoints which should only
Tabii ki bu tipik bir kullanm durumunda, yalnzca API tarafndan onaylanm kullanclar tarafndan kullanlabilecek belirli API
be usable by authenticated users,
u noktalarna sahip bir arka ucunuz
right now in our demo backend with firebase, that's not the case though.
var, u anda firebase ile demo arka ucumuzda, bu durum byle deil.
If we have a look at database which gives us our endpoints in the end, all the endpoints so all requests
Son noktalarmz bize veren veri tabanna bakacak olursak, tm u noktalar bu yzden tm istekleri o URL'ye
being sent to that URL and then any nodes nested beyond that are basically available to everyone.
gnderilir ve daha sonra i ie gemi tm dmler temel olarak herkes tarafndan kullanlabilir.
That is the case because earlier in the course, we changed our rules here to grant read and write access
Bu durumda, daha nce kursta, kurallarmz burada herkese okuma ve yazma eriimi vermek iin
to everyone here by setting this to true,
burada deitirdik, bunu doru olarak
we did this to be able to use that database without having authentication,
ayarladk, bu veritabann kimlik dorulamas yapmadan kullanabilmemiz iin yaptk,
well now we got authentication so we can finally change this back.
imdi kimlik dorulamas var. Sonunda bunu deitirebiliriz.
Now of course this is firebase specific that you do it with the rules set up, for your own backend
Tabii ki, bu, kendi API kodunuzu yazdnz kendi arka ucunuz iin
where you write your own API code,
ayarlanm olan kurallara gre yapabildiiniz
you probably have some if check where you check if some valid token is attached to the request and you
belirli bir firebase'tir. Muhtemelen, baz geerli belirtecin istee bal olup olmadn kontrol
simply return a 403 answer
edip etmediinizi kontrol etmeniz gerekir.
if that's not the case. Here however we do have these rules and in the simplest case, we can set this
Durum byle deilse 403 cevab verin. Ancak burada bu kurallara sahibiz ve en basit
to auth unequal null which simply means if auth is not equal to null, then read access is granted.
durumda, bunu haksz null olarak ayarlayabiliriz, ki bu sadece auth null'a eit deilse, daha sonra okuma eriimi verilirse anlamna gelir.
But in other words that means if you're not authenticated, then auth is null,
Fakat baka bir deyile, eer kimlik dorulamas yaplmazsa, o zaman auth botur,
therefore this returns false
bu nedenle bu false deerini
and you don't get read access,
dndrr ve okuma eriimi elde
the same can be done for write access.
edemezsiniz, ayn yazma eriimi iin de yaplabilir.
If we set it up like this, this is applied to the entire database, to all the data that's in there,
Bunu byle ayarlarsak, bu tm veritabanna, oradaki tm verilere uygulanr, imdi
now actually I want to give access to ingredients for everyone and just make access to orders only available
aslnda herkes iin ieriklere eriim vermek istiyorum ve sadece kimlii dorulanm kullanclara sunulan
to authenticated users.
siparilere eriim salamak istiyorum.
So for firebase what we can do is, we can fine tune our rules and we can say yes in general you got
Firebase iin yapabileceimiz ey, kurallarmz iyi bir ekilde ayarlayabiliriz ve evet diyebiliriz,
read and write access but then we can add a rule here,
genel olarak okuma ve yazma eriimi elde ettiniz, ancak sonra
nest this and say for the orders node and you have to name it exactly as the node is named, there
buraya bir kural ekleyebiliriz, bunu yerletirebilir ve sipariler dm iin syleyip adnz yazmalsnz.
I have a specific set of rules, there
tam olarak dmn isimlendirildii gibi, belirli
read access is granted only if auth is unequal to null
bir kurallar kmesine sahibim, okuma yetkisi yalnzca kimlik dorulamas
so if you are authenticated and the same for write access, that should also only be granted if it's
iin eit deilse ve bu nedenle yazma eriimi iin aynysa ve yalnzca eriim
unequal to null. So with that, we can publish these rules and that will now ensure that we do indeed only grant
eitse, bu yalnzca eriimin eit olmamas durumunda verilmelidir null'a. Bu nedenle, bu kurallar yaynlayabiliriz ve bu, artk sadece yazl olarak
write and read access to the ingredients to everyone but not to the orders.
sadece materyalleri herkesin kullanmna yazmay ve okumay deil, emirleri okumamz salyor.
However if we do it like this, our top level read and write rules will still overwrite this for any nested
Ancak bunu byle yaparsak, en st dzey okuma ve yazma kurallarmz bunun yerine yuvalanm
nodes so I actually have to get rid of that and instead I'll add a separate rule here for my ingredients
dmler iin bunun zerine yazacaktr, bu yzden bundan kurtulmak zorundaym ve bunun yerine malzemelerim iin ayr bir kural ekleyeceim.
and there I'll still set to read and write to true
hala okumaya ve yazmaya devam etmeyi ayarlyor,
but that means that only the ingredients now have read and write access or are open to everyone I should
ancak bu sadece yazlanlarn okuma ve yazma eriimine sahip olduunu veya herkese ak olduunu sylediim anlamna
say, orders is only available to authenticated users
geliyor, sipariler yalnzca kimlii dorulanm kullanclar tarafndan kullanlabilir ve kvaml kal malzemelerden
and I should add a comma here after the curly brace of ingredients. With that we can test it,
sonra buraya bir virgl eklemeliyim . Bununla test edebiliriz, eer bavuruma
if I go back to my application, reload it and go to orders, we get an error,
geri dnersem, yeniden ykle ve siparilere gidersem, yine de bir
if I go to the burger builder though, that still works.
burger reticisine gidersem hata yaparz, hala alr.
So the ingredients were still loaded,
Malzemeler hala yklydi,
I only get an unauthorized error if I visit orders here.
siparileri ziyaret edersem izinsiz bir hata alrm.
Now that is good,
imdi bu iyi, tam da
that is exactly what I want
istediim ey ve bununla birlikte,
and with that, we can now make sure that we can still reach orders if we are authenticated and have a token. To do that,
eer biz kimlik dorulamas yaplrsa ve bir jetonumuz varsa, emirlere ulaabileceimizden emin olabiliriz. Bunu yapmak iin, bu siparileri
I need to go to the place where we actually send this orders request and that of course is the action creators
gerekten gnderdiimiz yere gitmem gerekiyor ve tabii ki eylemler
in the orders file in the actions folder.
klasrndeki eylemler dosyasndaki eylem yaratclar.
There we have to purchaseBurger action and we also have the fetchOrders action, let's work on this one
OradaBurger eylemi satn almak zorundayz ve biz de fetchOrders eylemine sahibiz, ilk nce bu
first.
konuda alalm.
Here we essentially have to add our token, our token we got back from firebase when authenticating
Burada, bizim belirteimizi eklememiz gerekiyor, kimlik belirleme srasnda firebase'den geri aldmz simge
and then we can attach this token to this request.
ve bu belirteci bu belirtiye ekleyebiliriz.
The authentication is very simple then, we just have to add a query param questionmark auth equals to the
Kimlik dorulamas ok basittir, biz sadece bir sorgu param soru iareti auth eittir eklemek iin bir belirte gerektiren ve
URL we're making the request to which requires a token and then we have to pass the token. Now the token
daha sonra belirteci gemek zorunda olduumuz URL yapmaktr. Tabii ki burada elbette
of course here is the special thing, the token is stored in our redux store,
ki zel bir ey var, jeton
how do we get it here
bizim redux
inside our fetchOrders action creator?
maazamzda saklanyor, onu buraya getirelim.
Of course we could receive getState, you learned about this,
Elbette getState'i alabildik, bunu rendiniz, sadece
you can not only get your dispatch action, you can also get the getState function here which you can
gnderim ileminizi gerekletiremezsiniz, ayrca devlete erimek iin yrtebileceiniz getState
execute to get access to the state.
ilevini de alabilirsiniz.
I also taught you that I'm not recommending using that a lot and I don't want to use it here, though
Ayrca bunu kullanmay ok tavsiye etmediimi ve burada kullanmak istemediimi de rettim,
I see that this could be a case where it makes sense to get this information which doesn't really matter
ancak bunun sizin iin gerekten nemli olmayan bu bilgiyi elde etmenin
to your view
mantkl olabilecei
right
bir
in the action creator. Still, I want to get it in the place where we dispatch the fetchOrders
durum olabilir. Eylem oluturucuda saa bakn. Yine de, onu getirme ileminin gnderildii yerde
action and then simply pass it as an argument to this action creator.
almak istiyorum ve daha sonra bu eylem yaratcsna bir argman olarak aktaryorum.
So I expect to get a token argument in this function and then I attach the token here to my request,
Bu nedenle, bu fonksiyonda bir belirte argman almay bekliyorum ve sonra belirteimi
so the missing piece is to make sure that we received the token here when dispatching fetchOrders, fetch
isteime ekledim, bu yzden eksik para, fetchOrders' gnderirken jetonu aldmzdan emin
orders is of course dispatched in my orders container,
olmak iin, siparilerim kapsaycsnda elbette siparileri gnderir orada,
there at the bottom, we have onFetchOrders and here again, I now need to pass on some token.
altta, onFetchOrders var ve burada tekrar, imdi baz belirteci gemek gerekiyor.
So this token will have to be passed to this anonymous function we execute here and then passed on to
yleyse, bu jetonun burada yrttmz bu anonim fonksiyona aktarlmas ve daha
the action creator
sonra eylem
so finally we have to get the token in the place where we call onFetchOrders, onFetchOrders is called
yaratcsna aktarlmas gerekecek, bu yzden nihayet, onFetchOrders olarak adlandrdmz yerde belirteci almamz gerekiyor,
here in the componentDidMount method and now we need to make sure that we have the token when we
onFetchOrders burada componentDidMount ynteminde arld ve imdi biz Bunu sylediimizde belirte olduundan
call that. Now the token
emin olmalyz. imdi,
as I said as stored in our redux store of course, we store it in our auth state slice here, the token.
bizim redux maazamzda sakland gibi sylenen belirteci, auth state diliminde burada saklyoruz.
So all we need to do is in our orders container where we already have mapStateToProps I now also
Bu yzden tek yapmamz gereken, u anda mapStateToProps'a sahip olduumuz sipariler konteynerinde olduum iin imdi
need to get the token from my state.
de eyaletimden bir token almam gerekiyor.
So I'll name the prop token and I want to access state and now not .order because I'm not interested
Bu yzden prop semboln isimlendireceim ve devlete erimek istiyorum ve imdi deil. Sipariim, dizime bir baktmz
in the order related slice of my state
zaman, durumumun ilgili
instead if we have a look at the index.js file where we combine the reducers, the auth reducer which sets
dilim dilimiyle ilgilenmiyorum. js dosyas, indirgeyicileri birletirdiimiz auth indirgeyiciyi, belirte
up the state for the token, the auth reducer can be found on an auth property,
iin durumu ayarlar, auth indirgeyici bir auth zellii zerinde bulunabilir, bu yzden
so this is what we should access.
erimemiz gereken ey budur.
So in orders, I should access state.auth.token, like this.
Yani emirlerde, devlete erimeliyim. auth. Bu ekilde belirtin.
And now with that, we're making the token available on the token prop, I can now simply pass this on here with
Ve imdi bununla birlikte, jetonu token pervanesinde mevcut hale getiriyoruz, imdi bunu
this.props.token and it will emphasize that this is only one way of doing it,
bununla buradan geebilirim. sahne. belirteci ve bunun
the alternative would have been to use getState in the order action creator.
bunu yapmann sadece bir yolu olduunu, alternatifin sipari eylemi yaratcsnda getState kullanacan vurgulayacaktr.
With that though we should get the token and pass on here.
Bununla beraber belirtiyi almal ve buradan gemeliyiz.
So now if we save all our code and go back, it was still fail here because obviously when the app reloads
Yani imdi tm kodumuzu kaydedip geri dnersek, yine de burada baarsz oldu, nk uygulama tekrar
all tokens are lost.
yklendiinde, tm belirteler kaybolur.
So let's switch to sign in and quickly sign in with the user recreated a while ago, hit submit
imdi oturum amaya geelim ve bir sre nce yeniden oluturulmu kullancyla hzl bir ekilde
now we can verify on redux that we have a successful authentication and that in the auth state, we have
oturum aalm, imdi gnder'e tklayn, baarl bir kimlik dorulamaya sahip olduumuzu dorulayabileceimizi dorulayabilelim
a token,
ve bu
let's now head over to orders
durumda, bizde bir belirti
and as you can see we now successfully load the orders here again without an error,
var, imdi bir sipari verelim. Grebildiiniz gibi imdi bir hata
this error here on the right is an old one because now we successfully send the request with the
olmadan buradaki siparileri tekrar baarl bir ekilde yklyoruz. Sadaki bu hata,
token attached.
buradaki bir hatadr.
And you can actually see this if you open the network tab in your browser dev tools, there you can see
A tarayc sekmelerinde a sekmesini aarsanz, bunu grebiliyorsunuz. Burada tekrar siparilere
that if I go back to orders again, here's the request being sent where the token is attached, this is the very
geri dnersek, belirte eklendiinde gnderilen istein ok uzun URL olduunu grebiliyorsunuz. simge, URL'nin
long URL but because the token is part of the URL,
bir parasdr. Kimlik dorulamamzn nasl yaplaca
that is how we have to authenticate and how we can send our token to the backend.
ve simgemizi arka plana nasl gnderebileceimiz budur.
So this is now how we can use the token to access protected resources,
yleyse bu, korumal kaynaklara erimek iin jetonu nasl kullanabileceimiz, elbette, burada bir sipari
of course the same is relevant when we make an order here, purchaseBurger,
verdiimiz zaman, satn aldmzda, ayn zamanda satn almamzla alakal, ayn zamanda
there we also need to get that token as an argument in the action creator
eylemi oluturucuda bir argman olarak bu belirteci almamz ve sonra
and then add it as a query param to the URL we're sending the request to,
da isteinizi gnderdiimiz URL'ye bir sorgu parametresi, yani auth
so auth also should use the token here or the auth query param should be the token argument we're receiving
da burada belirteci kullanmal veya auth sorgusu param burada aldmz belirte argman olmal ve
here
bunun
and for that, we of course have to make sure that we do receive a token here too.
iin elbette ki burada da bir jeton var.
So we have to go to the place where we dispatch purchaseBurger and that of course happens in contact
Bu yzden satn alma ilemini yaptmz yere gitmeliyiz.Burger ve tabi
data,
ki
there we got our method for making an order, the orderHandler where we have onOrderBurger which
iletiim verilerinde var, orada bir sipari yapmak iin yntemimiz var, sipariteHerhangi bir sipari yarattmz
in the end dispatches this action creator, so there, purchaseBurger is dispatched.
orderHandler, sonunda bu eylem yaratcsn gnderiyor, yani satn alyorBurger gnderilir.
Now here we need to pass that token, for that
imdi burada bu belirteci
we need to receive it in our list of arguments of this method we're mapping in the prop and for that
gemeliyiz, nk bu yntemde argman listemizde yer almalyz.
we need to make the token available as a prop in that container too.
Bu metot, paftada eletirdiimiz yntemdir.
So just as in the orders container, I'll map a token property to state.auth.token
Yani sipariler kapsaycsnda olduu gibi, bir belirteci zelliini devletle eletireceim. auth. Simge ve imdi biz
and now we can go to the place where we do dispatch this, where we call the prop dispatching the action
bunu gnderdiimiz yere gidebiliriz, burada, OrderBurger'daki eylemi gnderen prop'u
onOrderBurger and also pass on this props token here.
ararz ve ayrca buradaki jetonlar da burada geiririz.
And with that, we're making sure that we are having a token and sending it,
Ve bununla birlikte, biz bir jetonumuzun olduundan ve gnderdiimizden emin oluyoruz, imdi burada
now here we get an error because the application reloaded hence the token is lost.
bir hatayla karlatk nk uygulama yeniden yklendi, dolaysyla jeton kayboldu.
But if I do sign in again and we'll take care about this auto logout we're having here soon,
Ama yine de giri yaparsam ve bu otomasyona dikkat edersek hemen burada oluruz, tekrar giri yaparsam
if I log in again I go to burger builder,
burger reticisine giderim, eer imdi burger
if I now build a burger here, order now,
kurarsam imdi sipari ver, devam et,
continue,
izin ver
let me clear the network tab,
A sekmesini temizleyin, burada da
continue here
devam edin
too and now let's quickly enter some data, like this.
ve imdi bunun gibi baz verileri hzl bir ekilde girelim.
If I now click order here, you'll see that was successful because it sends the orders request
Siparii imdi tklarsa, sipariin gnderildii istei gnderdii ve burada gnderilen iki istekle kartrlmad
and don't be confused by two requests being sent here,
iin bunun baarl olduunu grrsnz. lki,
the first one is just an options request which Chrome always sends if you're sending a post request.
gnderim yapyorsanz Chrome'un her zaman gnderdii bir seenek isteidir. bir posta istei.
This is the relevant one, this post request with the token and indeed we can verify in our database
Bu, ilgili mesajdr, bu yazyla birlikte talep edilir ve veritabanmzda,
that we got a new order here with the burger we just configured.
yeni yaplandrdmz burger ile yeni bir sipari aldmz dorulayabiliriz.
So this is now working, now we are using that token to reach protected resources
imdi bu imdi alyor, imdi korumal kaynaklara ulamak iin bu jetonu kullanyoruz ve
and as you can see when you reload the app and visit orders for example, it's not working if you don't
rnein uygulamay yeniden yklediinizde ve siparileri ziyaret ettiinizde grebileceiniz gibi, bir
have a token.
belirteciniz yoksa almyor.
Of course it's not the greatest user experience to
Tabii ki sadece bir sayfay ziyaret etmek ve sonra
well just visit a page and then fail.
baarsz olmak iin en iyi kullanc deneyimi deil.
It would be better if we can't visit pages where we need to be authenticated in the first place, of
lk etapta kimliklendirmemiz gereken sayfalar ziyaret edemezsek daha iyi olurdu. Tabii
course it would also be better if the UI would show us if we are authenticated and it would be best if we
ki, eer kimlik dorulamas yaplrsa kullanc arayznn bize gstermesi daha iyi olurdu
could also log the user in if there theoretically still is a valid token so that we don't lose our
ve eer oturum aabilirsek en iyisi olurdu Kullanc, teorik olarak hala geerli bir belirte
authentication state whenever we reload the application.
ise, uygulamay yeniden yklediimizde kimlik dorulama durumumuzu kaybetmeyiz.
These are all things we're going to tackle over the next lectures.
Bunlar bir sonraki derslerde stesinden geleceimiz eyler.